[Music]
Hey everybody. Welcome back to another
digital making at home video. This week
me and my sidekick Xavier... Hi. ...we're gonna
be doing some stuff in BlocksCAD, are
we? Yeah. So we're gonna be doing some 3D
design and BlocksCAD is a lot like
scratch... But it's all math. ...It's all math, isn't it? Yeah. Yeah, yeah,
so instead of like making animations or
things we just do heaps of 3d math tell
me lots of geometry. Which would be
tricky for you isn't exam ready done
that at school yet. So we had to do a lot of
learning didn't we to get blocks get to
work yeah but it was okay in the end
wasn't it and you make cool stuff so we
show these people how to do that today
loads of numbers yeah but we'll come to
that in a sec right cool so what I'm
gonna do is only get Xavier to drive now
and we're going to duck across here to
the project site so you can see what
we're doing we click browse all projects
and today for our software we want lock
scared so that's just it here and we
click on block scared and you see it
narrows down to these three projects
here and which one do we do today's a 3d
bugs fantastic so we open up that
project and we can see here as we go
down what you will make you'll make
these little 3d bug here but you can
mess around with your own one and change
the numbers but for ease of math we're
just gonna follow the instructions today
wrote it we made some cool stuff earlier
but today we're just going to keep it
simple so that everyone can follow along
so what you will learn today it explains
you here we're gonna do some 3d modeling
with geometric shapes mostly with
spheres which we're gonna stretch and
skew and do weird things and we're going
to use scale to make that happen
so the introduction was step forward so
say if you want to take over you can
just drive from here so if you follow
the project along and you click on the
blocks CAD comm editor link at the top
there where the first tick is it will
open up the blocks account editor that
means they've you've already got one
open so if you click that top tick so
that we've done it and then you can just
change tabs across to our blocks care to
show everybody where we've got it and
what it looks like we're giving a bit of
an explanation so you can see here the
blocks count is very similar to scratch
in the way that's laid out on the left
there you've got a bunch of menus to
show with menus as a yet one of the 3d
shapes and 2d shapes and you can see
they're laid out by color and as we work
through the project today our blocks in
the project instructions have exactly
the same
it does say math yeah there's loads of
math about to happen you can see in the
middle there's the workspace which is
where you drag all your code blocks and
there's only clip them together just
like scratch and join a show everybody
where the rendering space is it shows
our picture where's that that's here
isn't it and so we can see datum yeah
and so do you ever what the three axes
are called what the letters are they
have what's the sideways one it's the
same letter as your name Thanks what's
the up-and-down one and then third
dimension is Zed very good it took a
little while to get there didn't it
because when we work in scratch we have
X and we have Y and when we work in 3d
we have said which is depth okay so
there's a unity for the shape to get
bigger and Y goes up yeah the forth
enough depth fantastic so we're gonna be
working with depth today so if you
haven't done 3d geometry before at
school that's okay if you follow the
instructions it'll give you a nice
little primer on exactly what geometric
shapes are we're working with mostly
spheres which is what you get when you
make a circle and you take that out into
three dimensions and it becomes nice and
round like a ball shape so to start with
say if you want to go back to the
project so I just have a look at our
instructions what do we need to do up a
bit well the tab is that's it so we need
to start with what a sphere yet with
radius R fantastic millimeters it's a
tricky word that one right so for the
people at home what that means is when
you make a sphere in your project today
and this radius is 10 that will be 10
millimeters in the real world it will
translate out to about a centimeter in
the real world so what we're going to do
is click across me we're gonna make our
sphere with radius 10 so go back to
block scared that's it and drag your 3d
shape and we want to spear with radius
10 so drag that in that so on and save
you just pop that in the workspace so
how do we get everyone to see our
pictures if you want to click to show
the sphere we make a sphere in our
render space what's the button that we
have a click that's it so we click it
and it will make a sphere fantastic so
we've got to see you there that's radius
you change the color of is a square yes
go pick a new color yeah so what are you
gonna pick and that makes us fear blue
it's just a cosmetic and remembering
that when you three these printers ink
and what will it mean when it's 3d
prints what color will it come out or
why because if then will you have to do
it because that's the only piece of card
right so the filament that we have in
our 3d printer we're lucky enough to
have a 3d printer here at home and the
filament that we have is pink and black
so whatever colors you guys pick in your
project it won't come out on the 3d
printer but when you make those files in
3d they'll keep the color in the file
but 3d printing it's down to whatever
filament you have in your 3d printer so
picking colors here it does that's a
good question about 3d printing so
there's different kinds of plastic
there's PLA and abs are the two most
common ones we have PLA in our printer
and both of those we have black PLA and
we have pink PLA so when we print out
you get to pick what color out of those
two but when we're working in the
project today we can make it any kind of
color that we want and save that file
yeah cool so back to the project so I
could've got a sphere that's exactly
what I wanted us to do okay so you can
take that tick-tick-tick see it and go
down a little bit so now we're going to
take our sphere and you can see in the
instructions here we're going to be
using a dark blue block which isn't our
transforms in the transforms menu so we
want to stretch it out a little bit to
make a body shape so rather than it
being a nice round ball we want our bug
to be slightly I'm just about to say you
can make it that's gonna be the body
yeah cool so what we do is let's go back
to our project now and we're dragging
our scale block so that's a dark blue
block scale this transform yeah that's
it and we're gonna pop that in our
workspace you can see there's a green
very good one
when I take this out you can see you
agreement um yeah and that's how you
know it's gonna clip it
excellent so you know why because we
want to stretch it along the y-axis
we're going to take that Y number and
click in the little block there's a V
make it one point two okay so you got to
have the one before the decimal place so
one point two cool and then when you
click render it will change your picture
okay so it won't change automatically
have to click render and then it works
out what you want and if you grab the
picture and drag with the left mouse you
can move it around okay we can see that
our sphere is slightly longer than it
was before it you can't make a bit
longer if you want but we'll leave it
there for now today just to keep it
simple so you wanna show everybody how
you reset the view what's the thing you
click to put it back so we can see a
target yeah yep you click it there we go
resets our view so that if we
accidentally like spin upside down or
get underneath and we want to go back to
the way it was we just click the target
and a recess nice so let's go back to
our instructions we can tick that one
can we made have bugs body a little bit
longer can it down a bit so what we're
gonna do here is can you see how we're
gonna change another number now said
access and what that'll do is that's
gonna take a shape and it's gonna squish
it down a little bit it's not gonna make
it so around anymore it's gonna squish
the loop with flash and make it more
like a dirty but make it good like you
couldn't do that though if you wanted to
right yeah no it'll be flat right and be
- neither am i sort of defeats the
purpose cool so let's go back and change
our Zed number in our transform so just
in the last block there that's it yeah
so where it says Ed's I don't at the end
of your scale block that's it we're
gonna change that to 0.8 that's it and
then re render render and then again it
flattened out and we did that made it be
more squat for us so that's cool
she'll get back to our structures to see
what the next step is awesome so he's
our team yeah and then flatten the base
so what this means is when you do 3d
printing you need to have a nice flat
bottom on the thing that you're printing
because if it's got a round spherical
bottom when you try and print it
we printed we'll try and print that
unless you make support for it it will
just wobble over okay so we want to try
and remove that and make the whole
bottom of that thing nice and flat we're
going to cut it off with a zero about
zero if you go back yep quick and you
can see if you move down there's another
one what we're gonna do is not cut the
whole thing like the top we're gonna cut
on the on the line which is right just
there I'm gonna cut the bottom half off
our my sauce nice and flats going like a
heart shape
cool so let's go back to my structures
and have a look at what we need to add
so what's our next block we're gonna
make what shape is that save us save
that
yes yeah what shape is that the yellow
shape yeah it's a cube it's a cube so
we're gonna go back and we're gonna grab
a cube block from our 3d shapes this is
Q Betsy drag it in pop it down in the
middlee workspace anywhere it goes
that's fine okay let's go back to our
instructions I see what else we need to
add okay so we need a translate block
and so when we're working in 3d
everybody we can do things like rotate
and translate and what translate means
is you take your shape and you move it
around okay so we can move it up move it
down left right forwards backwards all
those sorts of things you can do yep no
no no but it's the same thing right it's
what you do when you're having game
we're translating that shape so we're
moving it around so let's grab a
translate block flip it so that's our
transforms just clip it around our cube
in a cube fantastic so let's move them a
part of it to make a little bit neater
people consider then not link it up
fantastic that's it
cool and so we're gonna make that cube
and we haven't rendered it yet which is
why our cube has it appeared so we'll do
that no little me no not just yet so
we're going to translate it and what we
want to do is we want to take that cube
and we want to drop it down in our said
axis so we want to put in our Zed square
we want to put minus 5 so pop minus 5 in
there's a minus 5 yeah negative 5 cool
and then let's go back because we want
to add go to transforms and we want to
add color so pick a color one and we'll
just
yellow for now because that's the way it
is in the instructions and clip it
around your cue block the one we just
made click that's it and the whole thing
up up up oh that's it
bang okay so moving the part again so
nice and neat fantastic and so now when
we click render we'll get our sphere
that we've already made and we'll also
have it render a new cube for us that's
yellow well but it's not quite right it
looks a bit wonky so let's go back and
our instructions have a look at what
numbers we need to pop in there so we
want - fire but what we want with our
cube is we want it to be 50 50 and 10
and the important theme the last thing
that drop-down menu that says centered
we need to make sure it's centered not
that the corner is at zero zero zero on
the center of our cube to be as you go
back and that has to take that way so
that it says then there we go fantastic
and we want to change those to just
leave that right we do leave that 50/50
there we go and so now if you move it
around say V you can see that we've got
a big cube which is fine the enormous
cube is fine we're about to turn that
cube into a big eraser that will remove
everything that's inside it so we want
to be as big as possible that's
absolutely fine it will cover all the
parts of the bug that we might need to
make in the future so let's go back to
my structures and work out how to do
that David you remember ok so click the
tip because we've made our cube and it
looks like that and that's fantastic
let's go down a bit if we want a
different blocks and what covers our
difference block it pop it's purple and
that's our set up source it operations
under the normal form no it's under set
or brush that's it click that one and we
want the difference so that's a - so you
can see it also tells you plus and minus
in the block so we want to - we want to
have everything - what's inside that
cube so let's pop our scale one in the
top so pop a sphere in the top hole so
you can move that into the middle of the
table that's it and drag that in that's
much easier to do so drag your way into
the top hole that's it
then the other one into the bottom hole
this one yeah and so what that will do
is before we click render let's explain
what we've done so we're going to draw a
sphere and it's going to be minus
everything that's inside where that cube
appears so if you render it now Xavier
render a shape that's all gone the only
thing we have left is the bit of sphere
that isn't inside the cube and that's
exactly what we want so awesome
you want to move it around show
everybody what your bugs body looks like
that's it's all gone from underneath the
zero so let's reset our view there we go
and we go back to our structures now
we're well on our way to making a bug so
we can click the tick there and we can
say add our head to the bug so what
shape is that bugs body what's the name
for that shape the bullshit we've been
saying it a lot it's fear very good so
what shape let's head B so yeah so yeah
so let's make us let's make a new sphere
so what could we do happy we cheekily
make a sphere very quickly ok there we
go we always want to work smarter never
harder so right click on there yet
that's it the blue block and click
duplicate and we get a whole new setup
so move that away so people can see it
ok so you'll see that we're we've got
that that sphere will be exactly the
same as the sphere that we've already
produced and we don't really want that
we want to have a smaller sphere so
let's change the radius numbers a B and
let's change that radius number down to
6 okay and so wise a bees doing that
I'll explain to you because when we work
in shapes if you have a circle okay the
radius is this point from the middle of
the circle out to the edge of that
circle okay and with a sphere the radius
is the point from the dead center of the
ball out to the edge of the ball and so
we're going to have one of our body
that's got a radius of 10 so from the
middle to the edges 10 millimeters and
another one where from the middle to the
edge is six millimeters so because if it
was 10 it'll be too big yeah well it'd
be the same size wouldn't it nobody's
got a head the same size of their body
yeah yeah so when we click render what's
going to happen why can't we see our
head level there we go interesting so
it's made it we can tell that it's made
it but it hasn't quite removed it yet
because it's not you know TAS look like
a hominem cutters good point man
so let's reset our view again let's see
the target there we go and so what we
need to do now is if you go to set up
say via and choose Union it's a purple
menu and Union that's the top one so
this is a plus so what we wanted to hear
I only have Union we're going to say
take this and this smoosh them together
make them one big piece and so I'm gonna
grab a sphere with radius 10 it's fit
yep so the one that we made inside our
difference block that's it grab it and
drag into the bottom hole of our Union
and then we took the new block that we
made into the top hole there the scale
that's it drag that one into the top and
then we put the whole Union block inside
the hot top hole of that difference
block okay so yeah so before we render
let's explain to everybody what we're
doing okay so what we have now is if you
press + is going the extra space see
yeah but we don't need that right now -
so clicking - that's a good point but
like let's do that when it's relevant
yeah just throwing information in and
confuse people it's good do you know how
to drive it man but let's run through
the instructions briefly yes okay cool
so what I'm gonna do now is if we click
render what it's going to do it's going
to join those two spheres together for
us just like this and it will chop the
bottom off them because they're all
inside that difference now so you can
see that it's got make us via mega
sphere and then remove all the cube
underneath now why can't we see the head
right so what we need to do with it we
need to once the one tur translate yeah
yeah we want to move it so let's go back
to our instructions and have a look okay
so we can click that tick because we've
got the feet sphere inside another
sphere so what I need to do is if you go
down okay and that one just there just
tells you so you can remove the body so
if you right-click on the body block you
can disable the blocks
it doesn't work and it will show you the
head but we're gonna skip that far yeah
cool so click that teacup there's only
the Milotic yeah and then down to the
next part so we're gonna translate along
the y-axis so get your transform and
grab your translate block that's it and
pop it in your workspace just in the
middle your workspace that's it grab
your top scale block so the one that's
for the sphere up up up let navy blue
block that's it no no let's on grab that
one and drag it into the translate block
change the number in the Y at the top
there to five yep
make let's say five cool and then drag
the whole thing back into the top okay
now when we render it should it's not
quite there yet
interesting so maybe what we need to do
is add a bit more to the wire let's see
if we can make that whine a little bit
bigger and see if the head appears so
that little number Y that's it click in
there you could stick 10 try it but
sometimes it can go owl the body there
it is that's pretty cool you can make it
bit wider but I wouldn't say well you
can do if you want me to scale it scale
it along the x-axis if you wanna make it
fatter just change that none that next
one down let's translate you want to
scale it let's see it's a scale means
that you're changing along one direction
you're making a fatter or narrower along
one direction x-axis would be a bit
fatter if you want go and then change it
scale it so you want to scale both of us
have ears along the X so you've got it
selected already if you make that number
slightly bigger one point something yep
the one you've already got selected so
you want to be one in a second over the
top number one so one point sure so now
render it again
and you see it will change the fatness
of his head for us now as a Mikey yeah
the body is the next one down so if you
scale the next one down change it down
here Denton that next one down and then
that's it where is his scale X yep the
one across in the
xblock and you can make that fat in
there too so one point I don't want to
make the head bigger
okay we're changing back in a minute
gonna make a body fat oh yeah don't put
one point something like point something
we'll make it smaller yeah
did you wanna make the head smaller you
happy with that nurse okay so that's it
change the scale there one point
something smaller maybe like one point
two okay
yeah and then render better yeah you're
diggin that awesome
can you make it like that yeah just
scale it up along the y-axis they'll
remember the more we play the numbers
the more we're going to have to think
about the maths later so I might be good
ideas for these purposes I mean we can
play with ours all we want later but
let's just leave this one simple for the
people at home okay so let's go back to
our instructions cool so you can click
that tick now because we've translated
our head out of the body all right so we
moved it along the y-axis we slid it
along the y axis which is translate so
now we can go back and change the color
of our head can't we just start making
it look cool and reminding everybody
so grab your color block just transforms
yep and you can grab that color block
yep and you can clip around the head one
which is the top block there yeah that's
it let go and then grab your other one
and clip it back in that's it okay cool
so now change that color of the head to
something else check it like red or blue
or black he gives your heart does
doesn't it
anything will do there don't spend too
much time thinking colorful right now
cool and then when you render and we
should see the head change color just so
we can detect that they're different
parts pow awesome looking good good
let's head back to my instructions X and
we can take that next box too so we
played there and remember everybody when
you 3d print it okay the colors we have
in block scared won't necessarily
translate to your 3d printer unless you
have any fancy 3d printers got like
multiple filament heads but how long we
have to choose before we start sewing
put the right
color plastic in so the next thing we
want to do is it gives you a challenge
here so you can change the color of your
mug body model so you just do that the
same way we change the head color you
just grab your color blocking drag it in
with it go so let's to create legs so
this is the next part we want to do we
want to try and create some legs oh yeah
we need to close right this is very good
you guys have zip for it astonishes so
we need to now make a pair of legs in
the bugs body so the way we're gonna do
that we're gonna make another CR and
we're gonna stretch this one out big and
narrow so it sort of having a nice
around we're gonna make it go like this
and it's gonna look like a pair legs you
know so let's do it now so let's add
another sphere so if we go to your union
block if you click the plus on your
screen there where it says Union click
the plus up there show everybody bang
right now we've got a new hole how do we
make a quick fear how do we quickly pop
a sphere in there yep loving it work
smarter not harder so right click on
scale duplicate Potter straight in yep
let's add a different color to it so
that we can see the legs will come out
of different color as well let's do
that's a grab another color block same
transforms in color to bring a bottom
scale block down at third sphere one we
just added yeah that's it then that's it
took them in there and pop your block
back inside that's it excellent okay so
you can leave that yellow that's totally
fine and then what we need to do is
we're going to make that sphere and
we're gonna make it really wide out on
your fat we're going to skew it out so
let's have a look at the instruction to
see what they recommend we do so we've
got here we've got a sphere and it says
there we want to scale it down so we
want to make the Y and the Z quite small
and we want to make our radius bigger
than the body so let's do that now let's
go back to our blocks so make the radius
bigger than the body so what's that last
nonetheless has radius ten let's make
that a bit bigger really is 20 well
that'll be massive his legs would be
twice as long as his body then that's a
bit too big 13 14 15 cool and then we
want to change our wine Zed numbers
before you do that change the wine said
numbers down to likes 0.3 I think and in
the last one 0.3 as well yeah
cool so what we've done there is we're
gonna have our X scale be one point four
when I have a Y scale shrink right down
and as head scale will also shrink right
down so when you render that now so you
should get a little yellow feet sticking
out there we go they cool even talked
about that it's cool legs yeah like it
you make it shorter if you want man just
change the radius okay okay you can do
any that's better yeah have you can that
be good okay so what we need to do now
is instead of make a bunch of different
legs we're going to make another sphere
and then instead of just like making six
different legs and I make another long
sphere but we're going to twist it a
little bit so it looks like he's got six
legs so let's click another plus in our
Union at the top there so we're gonna
make another hole in our union block so
across video and your codes over here
the top block where it says Union in
your code have a look in your blocks on
the workspace where's his difference
then next one down is Union click the
plus and again make two more spheres
okay so select your your legs there
where it says color yellow yeah
duplicate that block clicking for the
hole underneath yeah yep
and duplicate it again and click it into
the hole underneath there we go so there
we go so now we've made feeley's what we
have to do with them though we haven't
twisted them yet have we okay so we need
to go to some transforms and this one we
want rotate so translate is moving
around rotate is to spin it on the spot
okay so we're gonna grab a rotate block
and pop it in our workspace cool grab
your second color yellow block one in
the middle next one up that's it drag it
into the rotate and pop that back in
hopefully that's it whole thing and then
you can do that again with another
rotate block rotate then put your
color-block in yep and drag the whole
thing back in and then we want to do is
we want to change our rotate so in your
first one to in the middle there where
it says up a bit up a bit yeah so
in this block here yeah we won't change
that number to 30 and you'll see that
the little angular indicator will show
you what 30 degrees looks like that's
how much we're going to twist our legs
by and then for the next one we want so
well that's okay I make a 30 click yep
excellent 30 degrees and then for our
next one down in the Zed rotate down a
bit we're in the rotate block which is
zero degrees that's it in there we want
to change that one now you could put
minus 30 because we want it to turn 30
degrees the other way the other thing
you could do is you could say 360
degrees minus 30 is 330 degrees but
we're lazy so let's put in minus 30 when
you enter it will automatically change
to 330 degrees for you because it's
clever like that so now when Xavier
renders his picture gone takes a little
bit longer than more complicated bits
you add the longer it takes and there we
go nice one so let's go back to my
instructions but we can make like spiced
wing doors what's crazy stuff wrong but
we're on that time today we're right at
the end of our video now I've already
been half the house everybody okay
so third pair of legs and we've done it
and in the next challenge the next step
is to design your own bug and you can do
different stuff Konya we can make text
we can do all sorts of crazy things but
I'll add some bonus features videos
again like I usually do and I'll show
you how to put your name on it stuff
like that so once you've done that
everybody what you do to go back to
blocks CAD fantastic and then down this
bottom here we want to click it just yet
but we'll show you where it is so save
your show that generate STL button so an
STL is a special kind of file that you
use in 3d graphing and things like that
you can generate that file and just load
it into any 3d printer and a 3d botswana
maker for you yep yep generate is to
your button in the bottom corner
absolutely next to render that's right
so we click it and it makes us a file
you can see down here mine is called
untitled as a vias put on Todd because
we didn't name it so if you go up here
and you call it something else so we
call it like we can call it excellent so
now in just maybe a clicks generate sto
it will make a fire
with the name bug to do it again dick
there we go and then you can see down
the bottom left of our screen there it
says bug to which is the file that it
just saved so that's how to make a 3d
bug and what we'll do now is I'll go
downstairs and pop it in a 3d printer
and I'll get that on tape for you guys
so you can have a look at what a 3d
print and make the thing and there's
anything you want to add about making
the bug yeah
and when you make the bug and the legs
on the body you can make it really long
you can make I think when you make the
body a bit fatter and rounder and round
you can else we print it bigger yeah so
we can scale the economy so we can make
our file here and once you get on a 3d
printer you can scale it up and down
again so however big it comes out if
you've made it too big by accident you
don't want to use all that plastic or
mom or dad says you can't use that much
filament then you can scale it down
inside the 3d printer and print it nice
and small we work do that's a
complicated mess for a little dude yep
yeah you sure you did get it like do you
understand a bit more about geometry and
stuff now have 3d shapes and things work
yeah that's good man listen come again
MT d4 is flat gonna taper yep 3d is
round nice should we make some Pokemon
balls for 3d printer yeah I just do that
later a nice so let's say goodbye to
everybody for now and we'll see him next
time I buy game bye
[Music]
you